Seth P. Holcombe Papers 2012.0040
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Seth P. Holcombe Papers
Bulk, 1946-1953
undated, 1887, 1946-1953
2012.0040
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
2.5 Linear feet Five boxes of photographic prints and negatives
The Papers consist of approximately 350 photographic prints and 500 negatives of images of steam locomotives mostly of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, taken in the Hartford, Connecticut, area.
Holcombe, Seth P., 1918-2009
Biography
Seth Pomeroy Holcombe was born on February 15, 1918, the son of Harold Goodwin Holcombe and Ethel Monson Holcombe. He grew up in Hartford, Connecticut, one block west of the railroad station, where he would frequently visit the station master and inquire about the engines passing through. He graduated from Trinity College in 1941.
Mr. Holcombe was the Secretary and Registrar of the Morgan Horse Club, now known as the American Morgan Horse Association. He married Lucy B. Eaton on January 17, 1959, and lived in Simsbury, Connecticut, from 1959 to 1974, and then in North Granby, Connecticut, until his death. He was an active member and President of the Salmon Brook Historical Society, served on the Granby Zoning Board of Appeals and as Treasurer of the F.H. Cossitt Library, and was a member of the Granby Republican Committee. He was instrumental in organizing the Granby Horse Council. He compiled and published several family genealogies and an anthology of letters written from 1822 to 1842 by Nancy Smith Huggins Holcomb, his great-great-grandmother.
Mr. Holcombe was a member of the Hartford Railroad Enthusiasts and took photographs of steam trains of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and on excursion trips of other steam railroads in the northeast United States.
Seth P. Holcombe died on July 9, 2009.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The Papers were donated in March 2012 by Mrs. Lucy E. Holcombe of North Granby, Connecticut.
Arrangement
Series I consists of photographic prints, organized by size and thereunder by year and month taken. Series II consists of negatives, organized by a number on the envelope applied by Mr. Holcombe as the photographer; the negative envelope number reads consecutively so that negatives are organized generally by date.
Mr. Holcombe often wrote the negative envelope number on the back of a print. Some of the prints have a description written on the back but for many of them the only way to know of the place the scene was taken or other details is to cross-reference the print to the negative envelope.
Note that many of the negatives do not have a corresponding print and many of the prints do not have a corresponding negative.
Scope and Content
The Papers consist of photographic prints and negatives, almost all taken by Seth P. Holcombe from 1946 to 1953, with some undated, mostly of locomotives of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, taken at locations in Connecticut, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and the Maybrook, New York, railroad yard. Other locations, of photographs more likely taken in the 1950s, include locations such as Maine, New Hampshire, and Virginia.
Other railroads represented include the Boston & Maine Railroad, the Canadian National Railroad, the Central Railroad of New Jersey, the Central Vermont Railway, the Chesapeake & Ohio Railroad, the Delaware & Hudson Railroad, the Edaville Railroad, the Lehigh & Hudson River Railway,the Lehigh & New England Railroad, the Maine Central Railroad (leased by the Boston & Maine Railroad), the New York & New England Railroad (a predecessor railroad line of the New Haven Railroad), the New York Central Railroad, the Rutland Railroad, and the St. Johnsbury & Lake Champlain Railroad.
Don Ferry is identified as the photographer of photographs of the Rutland Railroad. George L. Heath is identified as the photographer of the New York Central Railroad photographs. Mr. Holcombe's mother, Ethel Monson Holcombe, is identified as the photographer of the "Ike's Train" photographs.
Unless otherwise noted all engines and trains are those of the New Haven Railroad.
Unless otherwise noted all photographs are in black & white.
There are a very small number of postcards in the collection.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Holcombe, Lucy E.; Boston and Maine Railroad.; Central Vermont Railway.; Hartford, Conn.; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad.; Photographic negatives.; Photographic prints.; Steam locomotives.
- Series I: Photographic prints, Bulk, 1946-1953; 1887, 1946-1953, undated,
  - Small prints, 1946-1953, undated
    - 1400 series Hudson, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified engine, 1946 February (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Engines: 1300 Pacific, 1377 Pacific, 3600 8 wheel switcher, 1400 Hudson, 3005, 1396, 1946 March (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Engines 1020, 1370 and 1377, 1946 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Engines 479, 1009, 1027, 1373, 3217, and 3405, possibly in Hartford, Connecticut, 1946 May (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Engines 479 and 1369, 1946 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Engines 0731, 1014, 1328, 1338, 3000, 3217 amd 339 at Newington, Connecticut, 1946 July (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Engine 455 in Willimantic, Connecticut; engine 1383 possibly in Hartford, Connecticut, 1946 September (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Engines 479, 1001, 1009, 1014, 1325, 1327, 1338, 3423, possibly in Hartford, Connecticut; Engine 3240 in Maybrook Yard; engine 1341 in Bolton Notch, Connecticut, 1946 October (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Engines 1000, 1009, 1372 and 3604 in Waterbury, Connecticut; engines 345, 1000, 1331, 1341, 1373, 3337 and 3405 in Newington, Connecticut; engines 1359 and 3208 in the North Railroad Yards in Maybrook, New York, 1946 November (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Engines 1009, 3244, and 3338 in the North Railroad Yards in Maybrook, New York, 1946 December (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Engines 3228 and 3337 in the North Railroad Yards in Maybrook, New York; engines 1377, 3208 and 3231 "coming out of Hartford;" engines 1311, 1325, 3228, 3229 and former Central New England Railway engine 153; Boston & Maine Railroad engine 308, 1947 January (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Engine 1000 at the East Hartford, Connecticut, sluceway; engines 359, 432, 1001, 3005, 3504 and 3559, 1947 February (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Engine 2446 at the East Hartford, Connecticut, roundhouse; engine 1332 at Bolton Notch, Connecticut; engines 1007, 3206, 3208, 3210, 3223, 3227, 3558 and 3562, 1947 March (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Engine 832 and others of the Central Railroad of New Jersey, possibly in Easton, Pennsylvania; Engine 1311 and 3208, location unknown; Engines 1000, 1001, 1341, 3210, 3221, 3219 and 3560, in Newington, Connecticut; Engine 1407 on the turntable possibly at the Maybrook, New York, railroad yard (one person identified in a print as Bob Marchant, 1947 April (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Engines 345, 359, 423, 1009, 1323, 1345, 3209, 3210, 3225, 3230, 3337, 3339, 3405, and 3558 in Newington, Connecticut, with prints of men working on the tracks; engine 1345 at East Hartford, Connecticut, bridge, 1947 May (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Engines 1311, 1312, 1349, 1380, 1387, 1388, 3233 and 3235 (with view of "Mr. Taylor," the engineer, in cab); engines 1388, 3206, 3335 (identified as the "Speed Witch") in Bolton, Connecticut; engines 1341 and 1351 in Bolton Notch, Connecticut, 1947 June (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Engines 1381 (identified as the "Gauset Special") and 3335 (identified as the "Speed Witch") in Bolton or Manchester, Connecticut; unidentified engines possible of the Canadian National Railroad in Amherst, Massachusetts; scenes of a railroad roundhouse in Brattleboro, Vermont, 1947 July (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Engines 1349 (east of Terryville, Connecticut, depot), 3011 ("backing into east end of Terryville Tunnel") and 3022, 1947 August (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Engines 462, 471, 3005, and 3339, 1947 September (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Engines 479, 1001 supplying heat to Freedom Train, 1349 at Terryville, Connecticut, 3019 at Plainville, Connecticut, and 3013 at Holyoke, Massachusetts (very likely a train excursion), 1947 October (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Engines 1327 and 1331 in Newington, Connecticut; engine 1349 in East Hartford, Connecticut, 1947 November (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Engine 1347 in Hartford, Connecticut, and an unidentified freight train, all snow scenes, 1947 December (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Engines 479, 3014, 3335, and 3423; unidentified train at "Boston Roundhouse,", 1948 March (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Engine 1300 with train 130, east of Bolton Notch, Connecticut; engine 2446 at unidentified roundhouse, 1948 May (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Central Vermont Railway 472 and New Haven Railroad engine 1371 at the Willimantic, Connecticut, railroad station; engines 1327 and 1361 in Hartford, Connecticut, 1948 May (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Engine 1324 and the "Sphinx Special," train 1300, probably in Hartford, Connecticut, (note that the "Sphinx Special" was likely a special chartered train for a Masonic group), 1948 June (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Engine 3022 at the Amston, Connecticut, station, 1948 July (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Engine 1300 near the Walnut Street bridge in Hartford, Connecticut, 1948 August (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Engines 455 and 1331 at Willimantic, Connecticut; the Delaware & Hudson Railroad's Mallet freight locomotive in Mechanicsville, New York; the Boston & Maine Railroad's engine 1450 at North Station in Boston, Massachusetts, 1948 September (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lehigh & Hudson River Railway engine 12 at Maybrook, New York, 1948 October (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Engine 1337 near Walnut Street bridge in Hartford, Connecticut; "Yard goat" engine 2353 at East Hartford, Connecticut, roundhouse, 1948 November (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Engine 3334 in Hartford, Connecticut, 1948 December (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Central Vermont Railway engine 475 at New London, Connecticut, station, with several boys and men near train, 1949 May (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Unidentified engine in Providence, Rhode Island; Lehigh & New England Railroad engine 0 at the Pen Argyl, Pennsylvania, roundhouse, 1950 April (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Trains of the Edaville Railroad, in South Carver, Massachusetts, 1950 June (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Locomotive 93, the "Exchange Club Special," of the Rutland Railroad (note that photograph was taken by Don Ferry), 1950 October (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Chesapeake & Ohio Railway engine 1201 in Charlottesville, Virginia, 1951 January (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Engines 13 and 76 of New York Central Railroad on the Harlem Division, one of them in, photographer identified as George L. Heath, 1951 March (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Engine 1004 in Newport, Rhode Island; engine 1357 in Lowell, Massachusetts; engine 1387 at South Station in Boston, Massachusetts, 1951 April (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Engine 1388 on the New Haven Railroad's "last steam trip," at stops in Boston, Massachusetts, New London, Connecticut, and New Haven, Connecticut; photographs include many with the train's crew, 1952 April (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Central Vermont Railway engine 470 at Willimantic, Connecticut, Palmer, Massachusetts, and Brattleboro, Vermont; rear of New Haven Railroad Budd RDC car on exhibition (location unknown), 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Maine Central Railroad/ Boston & Maine Railroad engines, including 3712, the "East Wind," at South Station in Boston, Massachusetts, station and various locations in Maine, 1952 June (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Boston & Maine Railroad locomotive 1441 at various locations in North Station in Boston, Massachusetts, and in New Hampshire, 1952 August (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Covered railroad bridge on St. Johnsbury & Lake Champlain Railroad, near Hardwick, Vermont, 1952 September (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Two color photographs of "Ike's Train" in Hartford, Connecticut, likely a campaign train used by Presidential candidate Dwight D. Eisenhower. Photographer identified as Seth Holcombe's mother, 1952 October (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Derailment of a freight car on siding just north of crossing with highway, east of Granby Center, Connecticut, 1953 May (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Engine 3016 at New Haven, Willimantic and New London, Connecticut, 1953 July (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Postcard with a drawing "The Old War Engine 'Texas,' Cyclorama Building, Grant Park, Atlanta, Georgia,", undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Postcard of an unidentified train wreck, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - New Haven Railroad engines, places unknown, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Rutland Railroad engines, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - New York & New England Railroad engine 45, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Large prints, undated, 1887, 1946, 1950
    - Canadian Pacific Railroad locomotive 30, possibly in Regina, Canada, covered in ice, ca. 1887 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Engine 1027 in unidentified location and engine 3217 in Hartford, Connecticut, 1946 May (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Engine 3 of the Edaville Railroad, photographer identified as Don Ferry, 1950 June (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Unidentified New Haven Railroad engines, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Duplicate of print of New York & New England Railroad engine 45 found in small prints, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
- Series II: Negatives, 1946-1952
  - Negative envelopes 2-59, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
  - Negative envelopes 60-161, 1947-1952 (Box 4)